There is a new web interface that can be used to access Puhti directly from a web browser.
Note that the web interface is still a beta-version which means there might be further changes.
Use you CSC username to log in.
From there you can access your files in Puhti and launch some applications.
More in-depth documentation is available in Docs CSC
The usual way to log in to CSC supercomputers is using a secure shell (SSH).
SSH can be opened in for example in the Command Line Interface.
In Linux and Mac that is known as Terminal.
We recommend to get familiar with the basics of a Command Line Interface,
which is a little more spesific interface
that lets you use the full power of a supercomputer.
We have documentation and an introductory tutorial on how to SSH to Puhti.
The links are in the description.
Mac and Linux come with an SSH client in the Terminal by default.
In Windows 10, there's something called the PowerShell.
It can be used, but it might not be fully compatible with our set up.
Therefore we recommend another software called MobaXTerm which is free to use.
Putty or CMDer can be used as well.
Installing these software may require admin privileges,
so you might need your IT support to do this for you.
If you do plain SSH, by default it might not allow displaying remote graphics.
On Linux or Mac you can just add a capital X or Y to your SSH command,
and it will tunnel the remote graphics from Puhti.
In Windows MobaXTerm has a way to do that,
or then you would need to install some other tools.
Sometimes you may edit files in your local computer and
want to copy the files to a supercomputer or vice versa.
You can use secure copy and RSync directly from the command line.
The basic syntax is scp or RSync, then source path, then target path.
The path in another computer needs to include the domain and the username at that machine.
RSync is available in MobaXTerm which is one reason
we recommend MobaXTerm for Windows users.
Sometimes a graphical user interface for transferring files is much more convenient.
For Windows FileZilla and WinSCP are good examples.
Installing them might require admin privileges.
MobaXTerm also has a file transfer functionality.
When downloading files they go by default to a home folder, which is in a weird place.
The tip is to first choose this home directory from the Settings tab.
Also Puhti web interface can be used to move files between Puhti and a local computer.
SSH-keys are used for example in some RStudio or Jupyter Notebook workflows.
You don't need SSH-keys for logging in to CSC supercomputers,
but they can make your workflows easier at some point.
A tutorial covers the setup for SSH-keys.
The link is in the materials index page.
The default workflow for editing files is to open an editor on Puhti.
With lot of files, for example when coding that is not so convenient.
For these purposes you can install a suitable editor like Visual Studio code
or configure Notepad++ so that they sync the files to Puhti.
We have some detailed documentation in docs.csc.fi
with instructions on how to set up such environment.
The tutorials about Accounts and Connecting continue from here.
They cover the basic use cases with easy-to-follow examples.
Check the links in the description!