CSC supercomputers have different disk areas that have their own specific purposes.
This lecture gives insight on where to keep your files
and how to move the data between Mahti and Puhti.
The disk ares have different quotas which means that
users cannot just create files anywhere and forget them.
The additional fast disk areas are for applications
that require lots of file input and output.
Here is a visual layout of two supercomputers and the file storage.
The box on the left represents Puhti and the other on the right Mahti.
Down below is a cylinder that represents Allas.
There are bidirectional arrows between these three objects
illustrating that data can be transferred from each service to another.
Both supercomputers have their own Lustre filesystem
that contain disk areas called home, projappl and scratch.
You can move files inside a supercomputer using commands mv and cp.
For file transfers between Puhti and Mahti you can use rsync or scp.
And for using Allas object storage there is a separate lecture and tutorial.
It is important to realize that if you have your files for example in Puhti scratch area
they will not show anywhere in Mahti unless you manually copy them there.
As pictured in the previous slide, the main disk areas in both Puhti and Mahti
are the user's home directory, scratch and projappl.
The home directory is personal, but projappl and scratch are
for the project's use and they are shared with your project members.
In scratch disk area there will be an automatic file removal system.
To keep your data and results safe move them for example to Allas
during the lifetime of your project.
These disk areas reside in the Lustre parallel file system
which makes them visible in both the login nodes and the compute nodes.
If you want to know how the Lustre file system works
you can find the link to Lustre documentation in the slides.
Lustre is good in handling lots of data at once, but not well suited for
repeatedly searching and reading small chunks of files.
The documentation in docs.csc.fi covers also the default quotas for the disk areas.
There you can find more information about the default quotas.
For example in home directory you can not have more than 10 GiB of space
and you can only have less than hundred thousand files in there.
Puhti and Mahti do not share any disk space.
You can copy your files to a different supercomputer using rsync or scp commands.
You can also put your data in Allas and download it from there to other supercomputers.
You will learn more about Allas in the later presentations and tutorials.
You can check the status of the disk areas that you have
with command csc-workspaces.
It prints a list of your disk areas with current capacity and the number of files used.
Each project have their own projappl and scratch areas
and they all will be printed out for you.
The first line is your own personal project.
In this example the user has 8 GB of files against 11 GB of quota,
and 17000 files against the 100000 files that is allowed.
Be aware that you may reach this 100000 file limit
if you install software with many files
Please pay attention to the disk usage,
as well as the number of files that you are using in your disk areas.
Note that with this command you can also check the paths
to your projappl and scratch areas.
Here is the visual layout of two supercomputers and their file storage again.
In addition to the main disk areas the supercomputers have fast local disk areas.
These mean the temp directories in login nodes and
then NVMe directories on some compute nodes in Puhti.
Remember that the Lustre filesystem is not good
in reading or writing a lot of small files?
That is what the local fast disk areas are for.
In login nodes it is called temporary directory and
you can access it from the login node with command cd $TMPDIR.
The temp directory is meant for preprocessing of your files.
For example if you have too many files and you want to merge them.
Don't do any heavy computing in the login nodes.
In some Puhti compute nodes the fast local disk areas
have NVMe-based disks i.e. SSD-disks.
You can use them as part of an interactive job or a batch job.
The environment variable used for accessing the NVMe-disks
during a job is $LOCAL_SCRATCH.
You must copy the data in and out the NVMe space during your batch job
because the fast local disk areas are not part of the Lustre filesystem.
Otherwise the data and results produced during the batch job
will not be accessible to you after the job has finished.
You should consider using the NVMe space if your job reads or writes lots of small files.
Depending on the amount of files you might get up to 10 times faster performance
if you use the local fast disk area compared to the Lustre filesystem.
This slide shows a summary of the disk areas and their specific usecases.
Allas is for storing data that is not used in any computational analysis at the moment.
Home directory is especially meant for storing your personal information
and some scripts that you would like to use later.
Other users cannot access your home folder.
In projappl users can store their scientific programs,
binaries and packages with colleagues in the same project.
The scratch area should be your main working space for your scientific work
and it is also shared with project members.
The temp directory in login node is used for compiling code
and fast file I/O in lightweight processing.
NVMe disks are used in heavy computing
for fast file I/O in batch jobs or interactive jobs.
Do not put any databases on the Lustre filesystem.
It is not good to have too many files and
Lustre is inefficient in reading small bits of a single file.
For databases we recommend that you use our services
like Kaivos and MongoDB in cPouta.
Don't create a lot of files in one folder,
or actually don't create overall a lot of files in Lustre filesystem.
If that is needed you have to rethink the workflow.
Please note that CSC does not backup your data.
The disks are fault tolerant,
but that does not stop you or your colleaques accidentally deleting everything.
A pro-tip: modify the usage rights to files with chmod.
If your workflow requires reading or writing lot of files, use the fast local disks.
That will increase the performance for your computation,
as well as decrease the load on Lustre filesystem.
The documentation in docs.csc.fi contains best practice tips
for performance when using Lustre.
The tutorials about disk areas continue from here.
They cover the basic use cases with easy-to-follow examples.
Check the links in the description!