Allas is a CSC service and to use it you need to have a CSC user account
which is a member in a CSC project.
And then just like for Puhti and Mahti, you apply for the Allas service.
Allas is available for all project members after they accept the Allas terms of use.
Note that you can use Allas without Puhti or Mahti
if you only want to store files for your project.
Allas is a general purpose storage system, where files are stored as objects.
It is developed at CSC to provide a long term data storage space
for computing and cloud services.
It is a CEPH-based data storage system - in case anyone asks.
Allas is accessible from the CSC computing environment
and personal computers as well.
It is meant for storing your datasets during your project lifetime.
The default Allas storage quota for one CSC project is 10 terabytes.
If you need to have more quota and you have good reasons for that,
you can apply for more.
For that you need to send email to the CSC servicedesk,
but don't be shy to let us know if you really need the space.
The biggest projects have several hundreds of terabytes of data stored in Allas.
It is better to use Allas for storing large datasets rather than, for example,
applying for more scratch space for just having some data available for you.
Puhti and Mahti have clients for accessing Allas,
but Allas not in any way bound to other CSC services.
You can upload data and use Allas directly from your PC
or from your organization's own computing system.
Just note that there you have to install yourself the clients that you use.
So Allas is in a sense a some kind of data hub of CSC.
The illustration shows that you can access Allas from Puhti and Mahti.
Other examples are a weather measurement station
where the sensors send the data directly to Allas,
an university computer server, a Virtual Machine in cPouta,
a personal computer, a mobile phone and a web page.
So it does not need to be CSC involved in the process of moving data.
As long as you are connected to internet, you can use Allas.
The usual workflow is to have the static dataset stored all the time in Allas
and copy it to a computer to do some analyses.
And then put a new or another version of the dataset to Allas
if it has been modified somehow.
Files in Allas can be shared publicly to Internet.
For example these slides are stored in Allas.
Check the URL from the video description.
Allas is not a file system or disk.
Many of the interfaces represent the data like it had some hierarchy
- directories, subdirectories and files -
but in practice it is just a pile of static data objects.
You can add, read and delete objects, but you are not modifying any data there.
There is no real hierarchy
- it is just a place where you have some data blobs stored.
Allas is also not a data management environment.
The tools for searching data,
doing version controlling or metadata management are minimal.
The basic Allas command line tools can handle maybe
some hundreds of objects in Allas.
Workflows that automatically collect data to Allas and store it for a long time
will end up having hundreds of thousands of small files.
They will need some other tools to keep track of the data stored in Allas.
You can store huge amounts of data to Allas,
but we recommend to set up some support service like a database
that tells you later on what data is where and how to access it from Allas.
Also, Allas is not a back-up service.
If you ask where to have a copy of your important files in ProjAppl,
we will suggest to make a copy to Allas.
Nevertheless we want to point out that it is not a full backup,
because you or your colleagues can still accidentally delete the data from Allas.
All the project members have equal rights to the project's data in Allas.
You have to make sure that your project members know how to use the service
and agree on files that should not be deleted.
Note that all it takes is just one erratic command
- from you or your project members - and the data is lost.
Always keep important backups in a safe place
- for example in a separate local hard drive.
Allas is not a final resting place of your data
- the point is that you can have your data there
while you are actively working with that data -
which is sometimes several years.
Technical-wise Allas is quite secure.
Data is stored into several servers in Allas.
Individual disc or server breaks will not result to data losses
because other discs or servers have another copies.
Note that even these multiple copies of data do not help
if the user deletes the file or object.
We at CSC cannot recover your deleted data from Allas.
Storing data as static objets means that they can not be modified while they are in Allas.
If you want to edit a file you have to download it to some other environment,
for example to your local laptop.
Then after you edit the document you can overwrite the file in Allas.
You can use some data management and metadata features included in Allas,
but they have somewhat limited features.
Allas storage space is given for a CSC project
- sometimes referred as Allas project.
If your project has only one user then the data is accessible by you only,
but that is rarely the case.
Each project can have up to 1000 of so-called buckets.
A bucket is kind of a root directory in Allas.
Some interfaces may refer to buckets as containers,
but that confuses easily with Docker containers!
Each of the bucket names must be unique throughout all Allas.
This is because the bucket names are used if you generate
public URLs for your buckets.
Therefore two projects cannot have the same bucket name in use.
Keep this in mind when creating buckets and include for example
your project number in the bucket name
Then you can be quite sure no one else has a bucket with the same name.
If you try to use already used bucket name the system gives you an error message.
Data is stored in a way that is called as an object, which is like a static blob of data.
In general you can think that one file is one object.
That means that in a normal bucket an object name equals to a file name,
and you can pull the file to you environment by pointing the object name.
Then for example larger files might be automatically stored as several objects in Allas,
but in practice you don't have to worry about that.
Objects have metadata and users can add or edit their own metadata.
Each bucket can have half a million objects.
It sure sounds a lot at first, but if you have an automatic data collection service,
you may end up having these many files.
We ask you not to have these many objects in your buckets,
because it will make the system very slow.
It is better to create more buckets and spread the files among those.
The one level of hierarchy means that there can be only objects inside buckets,
not buckets inside buckets.
You can have object names which look like
that there is some directory structure there.
For example if the object name is maindir/dataset/data
where maindir and dataset are like pseudofolders.
Still there is no real directory structure there
- instead it is a long object name with directory names and slashes.
All in all you may think your project's Allas space as a home folder.
In there you have up to 1000 folders – here buckets – that have files
– but not real subdirectories.
There are several tools to interface with Allas.
Those tools use either S3 or Swift protocol for uploading and downloading data.
Both of them have their pros and cons, and you can use either one of them.
For the end user the biggest difference between S3 and Swift is in the authentication.
When you open the connection to Allas you have to authenticate first.
S3 protocol creates a permanent key for accessing your project's data in Allas.
These keys are always project specific and permanent.
The same can be used from any client to access
the project's data in Allas until you delete the key from the system.
It is convenient for a user, but also very unsecure.
If anybody steals your key - which is just a two random character strings
- they can access all the data in your project.
It means they can also delete all the data and you won't even notice it.
Swift protocol also has a random string used for authentication
but it is a temporary token.
The key is valid only for a limited time - currently eight hours.
After eight hours, or if you close the terminal session,
you need to generate new key with your CSC password.
It is perfectly fine to initiate a new connection already before eight hours have passed.
If somebody gets access to your Allas keys used by Swift protocol,
they have only eight hours time to do something.
Then if someone gets your CSC password
– well that is not good also for many other reasons.
In Puhti and Mahti environment we are preferring Swift for its safer authentication.
The two protocols also manage metadata a little bit different way.
And they handle large files also a little bit differently.
Swift protocols split your data in smaller pieces
so that you can easily read only part of it if needed.
S3 instead stores everything in a one big object.
Because of these differencies you should avoid cross-using Swift and S3 based objects.
That means if you have uploaded the data to Allas with one protocol,
it is better to also read it using the same protocol.
These Allas clients listed in this slide use either Swift or S3 protocol.
Many of these tools can actually use both of the protocols.
In Puhti and Mahti, we are mostly using command line clients
like rclone, swift, s3cmd and a-tools.
In your local Mac or Linux computer you can also use the same tools in Terminal.
In Windows and Mac you can use at least
Cyberduck, FileZilla pro, Pouta web-interface or SD-Connect.
You can also use FUSE-based virtual mounts
which makes one bucket in Allas to be shown as a directory.
That is handy especially in virtual machines.
It is also very prone for errors,
and we suggest you use only the Read-Only mode with this kind of approach.
First you have to enable Allas service in my CSC.
In Puhti or Mahti environment Allas is available as a module
which includes the Allas tools.
Load the Allas module with command module load allas.
Then run the command allas-conf, which by default opens a swift-based connection.
The configuration process asks you to specify a project.
The connection stays for eight hours and you can start
to figure out what was the command to see your buckets and files.
Check out the material bank for tutorials and a hands-on Allas tutorial video.
A straight-forward command line interface that can be used with Allas is rclone.
It works fast and provides functions like move, copy, tree and cat.
You can install it to all operating systems.
Be mindful that rclone overrides and removes data without asking.
That means you have to know which copy of your file is the newer version.
Rclone does not ask that "do you want to override this new file with this older one?"
– it just copies what you write in the command.
And then if you have a very large sets of objects then
it does not always function properly.
We have found that rclone has difficulties to list for example datasets
which have tens of thousands of objects in a one bucket.
By default at CSC rclone is configured to use swift, but S3 can be used as well.
We at CSC have created a wrapper around the native rclone.
The aim is to make the scripts more easy to use in Puhti and Mahti.
For example it uses default bucket names so you don't have to.
If you do not define a bucket name,
it checks that your data is coming from e.g. Scratch directory of Puhti
– and it creates a Scratch bucket for your project and puts the data there.
A-tools also do ask before overwriting or removing data.
The basic use case is that you use data from Puhti or Mahti, make a copy to Allas,
and later on download the data back to Puhti or Mahti.
You can install these tools to other Linux and Mac machines as well.
But note that a-tools are developed with CSC environment in mind.
For example it collects the directories in the one tar package and
does compression before uploading to Allas.
If you want to then push the data out to some other service,
it may require extra steps for uncompressing and unpacking the data
before you can access the files.
This is also a comparison of a-tools and rclone.
As stated in the previous slide, a-tools work nicely in the CSC environment.
It packages the data nicely and allows you to store and move it
in a bigger chunks instead of file by file.
The file size is reduced with compression,
so you can store more data consuming less billing units.
With a-tools you don't need to think about bucket names.
The default bucket names refer to Puhti and Mahti directory structures.
A-tools also prevent you from accidentally overwriting your data.
The downsides of a-tools are mainly related to the usage
in other that CSC environments.
Trying to read an object that is created with some other tool is usually complicated.
Objects created with a-tools have an additional .ameta metadata object.
A-tools put them in your bucket in addition to the object itself.
Then some practical good-to-know issues concerning Allas in general.
First of all is this eight hour connection limit with Swift.
It usually is not an issue in normal interactive work,
but in batch jobs you need to take that into account.
It might be that your batch job does not even start before the eight-hour limit has gone.
In batch jobs you should configure Allas so that it stores your password
in an environment variable in the session.
Then the Allas connection can be refreshed by the batch job
by using the password from the environmental variable.
Check the material bank for a tutorial on how to achieve this.
In Allas you cannot check the quota to see
the maximum amount of data you can have in Allas.
If you increase your quota from the 10TB default
there is no way to check the quota in Allas.
You can check the emails from CSC telling that
you have been granted 50 terabytes of quota.
If you try to put there data that exceeds the quotas it will tell that object is too large.
Then you might guess that you have hit the size limit of the Allas area.
Moving data inside Allas is not possible, at least with the swift protocol.
If you want to move a dataset from one bucket to another
or from one project to another, in practice you have to download it to
for example Puhti Scratch and then push it to the new location in Allas.
That is of course more time consuming that it would be
to move the data only inside Allas.
Freezing the data means such a read-only mode
that would prevent others modifying the data.
To achieve that in Allas you could use a so-called
'two project protocol' as a workaround.
The first Allas project is the hosting project.
The managers has full access rights to data under that project.
They can set up another project for the users of the data.
The users don't belong to the data hosting project,
so they don't have full access to all the data.
The managers can grant access for a selected users to e.g. one single bucket.
This way you can have more secure way of
sharing your data with your project members.
Another option is that you create a separate front server inside or outside Allas.
With the server you can control the access to data that you have in Allas.
For example you can set up a NextCloud server in cPouta,
and use that to share data to your external collaborators somewhere else.
It is a good idea to learn one Allas interface like a-tools and
stick with that as much as possible.
If you need to use many different interfaces,
keep in mind that they may work in a little bit different ways.
For example different CyberDuck versions show the data in a little bit different way.
You may not always see the same buckets and objects there - even though you should
- because the interfaces interpret the pseudofolders differently.
Whenever you plan to store something in Allas you should think
whether to store individual files, or to collect them in larger chunks.
Think about how you will use the data.
If you use a set of scripts that consist of three files,
you should collect those files to a one tar package,
and upload the package as one object to Allas.
Then you can download the files as one object which puts less stress to the system.
Consider also using compression to reduce the space needed to store the data.
Tt also reduces the time to move the data in and out of Allas.
That is especially good thing if you have a slow or unstable internet connection.
Compression of course takes time, so it may not bring time efficiency
You should also think of who can use the data.
By default all project members have equal access to the data.
Usually that is the ideal situation.
If not, then consider using two projects or another server to manage access.
Note that Allas is not the final resting place of your data.
When you start a CSC project you should already consider
what will happen to the project's data when the project ends.
Remember that the project lifetime has to be extended
yearly if the project still continues.
After the project is finished you need to save everything in somewhere else,
because everything will be removed from the CSC environment
- which means from Allas as well.
In time you start to accumulate large amounts of data in Allas.
It will get difficult to keep track of all the data you have.
You should plan and make rules on how to store the data in the Allas project
already before starting to use Allas.
Especially if there is a whole group pushing files and datasets to Allas,
it will get messy after a while.
A few words about other data services at CSC.
Allas is not the only place where you can store data.
The Fairdata services are more focused services developed with datasets in mind.
You can use them when you have a ready static data set that you want to
store for longer time, and make it available for other researchers as well.
Fairdata services consist of three main services.
IDA is the storage service,
where you can do things like data freezing and backup copies.
Linking to IDA there is Quvain for describing the data.
There are rich metadata features and a possibility to create
a persistent identifier for your data, which you can use in your publications.
Then there is the Etsin service, which allows external users to look for
the datasets stored in IDA and described with Quvain.
The datasets do not need to be accessible to everybody.
People can see that the dataset they need is there in IDA, and who has access to it.
Then they can contact the manager to ask for access to use the dataset.
Sensitive data services at CSC are intended for working with datasets
that contain sensitive or secret material.
In the core of the service is SD Desktop - Sensitive Data Virtual Desktop.
You can use that to work with sensitive data secure way.
The data is imported to the system through interface called SD-Connect.
The fact that you cannot access internet
or pull out data from SD Desktop makes it more secure.
It is possible to have a collaboration project where you let your collaborators do
analyses with your data, but never get the data out of your control.
In practice you can use Allas for storing sensitive data,
but you have to always encrypt the data before you upload it to Allas.
SD-Connect does encryption automatically and in a way
which is compatible with the SD-Desktop.
The tutorials about Allas continue from here.
They cover the basic use cases with easy-to-follow examples.
Allas documentation covers the introduction to Allas and the technical details.