Why should we care for Singularity containers in HPC environments?
In HPC centers applications are often installed as containers.
CSC makes no exception to that.
There may be slight differences in how you use regular software
and software in a container.
Check the documentation of that particular software
to see whether it is installed as a container.
Users also benefit from the use of containers.
They can install software easily - no need for HPC admins.
If a container with desired software exists,
users need only a single command to install it.
Let me tell you an example usecase where containers can solve the problem.
A scientific developer writes some code and wants to hand it over to a friend for testing.
The friend tells the developer that the test code is not working in the test environments.
Turns out the first test environment has slightly different versions of the used libraries.
The second test environment has a different operating system.
How to make sure that same code works on your computer
and in HPC environment or cloud environment?
That is the challenge that containers are going to solve.
Basically if something works on your computer,
it should work anywhere regardless of the underlying host environment.
A container packages everything needed to run the application
- i.e. their code and all dependencies.
The container image can be run like a binary file.
There are many container platforms around.
The most popular container engine is probably Docker.
Singularity is very popular in HPC environments and it is used also in CSC environment.
Both containers and virtual machines are solving this dependency issue.
The comparison here shows three ways of deploying your applications.
First is the native application - i.e. you compile and launch it.
Then it depends on your environment whether it works or not.
The second one is the virtual machine approach.
Virtual machine applications are usually rendered
through a special software called hypervisor.
Virtual machine includes OS and Kernel like a normal computer.
It basically is a virtual computer and there you can install everything from the scratch.
Another user can install the saved image of the system
and use it with good compatibility.
Third option is the container approach,
which is a bit more lightweight than a virtual machine.
You just install the container engine, but not kernel or any operating system.
So the key difference between virtual machines and containers is how they use kernel.
Containers share the kernel with the hardware,
whereas virtual machines have their own kernel.
From the user point of view: virtual machines boot the operating system
which takes time, and containers can be loaded in milliseconds.
Virtual machines are useful if you need to run a different
Operating System than your regular system.
You may have MacOS or Linux and then you need some Windows software
- so you can install Windows into a virtual machine and run that on your Mac.
If you need to use Linux from another OS you can
open an SSH-connection to Puhti or Mahti.
But that you probably knew already!
Containers can not run a different OS because the share the kernel with the host.
They can have their own libraries - and that is how they solve the dependency issue
which I described earlier with the example code test case, remember?
No?
Containers can have a different Linux distribution
- like Centos or Ubuntu - than the host has.
Containers are popular e.g. because they provide an easy way of distributing software.
They can be used like binary files,
which means that once you have the container you just run it.
Including all the dependencies inside the containers makes it portable and compatible.
Singularity containers can be run as a normal user
so they work nicely in HPC environments.
In comparison, Docker containers are inconvenient in HPC systems
because they require root access to run.
Users do not have root access in multi-user IT environment, like HPC environments.
In general all containers need root access when built.
For that you can use your local computer in which you probably have the root access.
There you can install all the packages that you want inside the container.
Then you can copy the container into CSC enviroment
and run it there with normal user rights.
That provides a convenient way of transforming your code
- with all your custom libraries - to the supercomputer.
While sharing the kernel with the host, containers have their own environment.
That means they can have different Linux distribution
which can include different libraries.
Your code might require Centos while the host has Ubuntu,
so you can have Centos in the container.
There might be some exeptions to that e.g. when working with GPUs or MPI libraries.
Still in general containers solve many incompatibilities
and are less likely to be effected by changes in the host system.
Containers ensure that your computational environment
and your collaborators environment are the same.
You can save a whole analysis environment,
which means e.g. all the libraries and their versions.
That means you can easily share the environment with collaborators as a single file.
Singularity is a container platform like Docker
Singularity containers can be run with a basic user level rights.
Note that you cannot elevate your user privileges inside the container
- which is also good from administration point-of-view.
Containers are faster to deploy than virtual machines
because they only load the libraries, not a full operating system.
Singularity containers support MPI,
but make sure to use compatible MPI libraries inside the container.
Here compatible means the hosts should have at least the version
which is available in the container.
Singularity can use also a driver stack e.g. when using GPUs.
That means you don't need to install drivers inside the container,
but the container can use the driver that is already available in the whole system.
Option --nv tells the container to use driver stack.
There are a lot of Docker images around, because Docker is very popular.
You can convert Docker containers into Singularity containers
and use that also in an HPC environment.
In general containers should be run as a batch job or an interactive job.
Singularity commands are available also in the login node - no need to load a module.
Users can always bring their own containers and start using them right away.
Some software in Puhti or Mahti are installed as containers.
Always check software information in DocsCSC for details on usage.
There is only three commands needed for running Singularity containers.
The first one is singularity exec with container name
and a command that you want to run in the container.
It let's you to use same commands that you use
for your application also with the container.
Command singularity run runs the default action of the container.
The default script is defined when building the container.
If you want to interactively work inside the container
- instead of the host command line - you can open a command line
inside the container with command singularity shell and the container name.
Then you will be in a different file system environment that is built inside the container.
The container file system includes the files that are put there when the container is built.
You can always go inside the container and check out the file system there.
Usually containers are read only systems
which means you cannot change the files inside the container.
Often the container needs to access some files in the host computer.
To do that we can mount or bind host directories inside the container.
Note that they are writable so file changes there are permanent.
To mount a directory into a container use the flag --bind.
If the target directory - in this example /data - does not exist, it is created automatically.
If you don't define the target directory it will use the host directory name by default.
If you need to bind more than one host folders to a container,
just write more folders after the bind flag.
Environment variables like HOME and USER get their values typically
through some functionality built into the operating system.
Most environment variables are inherited by the containers.
HPC systems generally have many environmental variables
and some of them might interfere with your container.
If you want to prevent the container inheriting all the environmental variables
you can use flag clean-env.
However you can define environment variables
so that they are used only in the container.
Defining an environmental variable singularity env test in the host creates
such a variable that it shows as test inside the container.
Already worrying too much about mounts and variables?
Fear not!
We at CSC provide you with a special wrapper for this singularity application.
This singularity_wrapper takes care of common binds so you are able to see
your home, scratch and projappl directories inside the container.
Here this image.sif is the container image file.
Most modules also set this singularity image as special environment variable.
Then you do not need to write the image name the wrapper command.
A lot of applications are written as Docker containers.
I already mentioned that you can use the Docker containers in Singularity.
The command singularity build and the docker address converts
a Docker container in to a Singularity container.
You can do that with basic user privileges - which is dope.
Let's take this PyTorch image as an example.
You can define the name for the new converted Singularity container by yourself.
But the name of the source Docker container has to match to the one
that exists in the original repository.
So have the address right.
Check the documentation about running containers and
creating Singularity containers from DocsCSC.
It is quite clear already that Singularity containers provide
a convenient installation method, especially in HPC environments.
If the software exists as a container, use that and you do not need to worry
about the dependencies, because they can get very complex sometimes.
Also some old versions of the dependency softwares may be
incompatible with the host environment.
For example with scientific publications it is important
that you can reproduce the results even after a few years.
Going back to same data analysis with same libraries and versions
after many years could get tricky.
With containers you can ensure that you have the same image
and running it leads to similar results.
Consider using containers even though other methods were available.
Here is an example of a software that has three methods of installation
in CSC computing environment.
The first one is the native application compiled from the source code.
When installed it consists of 47 files with total size of 1.9 MB.
The second option in comparison is Conda which is quite easy to use.
Installing the same software with Conda results in 27000 files with total size of 1.1 GB.
With so many files it hammers the Lustre file system and the whole Puhti slows down.
We have written a DocsCSC page telling why you should not use Conda.
Then the point of this comparison: Singularity container.
There you have only one file - the container image - with total size of 339 MB.
So containers may get quite big which may limit the usability sometimes.
But remember that the container has also the dependencies installed.
With only one file it is Lustre-friendly and user-friendly.
In case you don't find a container that you want to use,
you might need to build your own.
It is a bit more involved process and requires root access
so you need to use your own computer.
You can start the building with the sandbox mode - if you want.
Open a shell inside the container to do the software installations.
If the base system is Ubuntu, you can use apt
or then in CentOS use yum to install packages and dependencies.
Consult software developer documentation for spesific instructions.
You can build the production image using the sandbox version.
Another option is that you write a definition file which is kind of a recipe of the container.
Once you have the production image,
you can transfer it to CSC environment and start working.
The tutorials about containers continue from here.
They cover the basic use cases with easy-to-follow examples.
Container documentation covers the introduction to containers
including technical details.