A CSC account is needed for using CSC supercomputers.
To get started, please find the links to tutorial and the documentation
that guide you with the account creation.
Keep the account valid by renewing the passphrase annually.
You will get a reminder by email.
Never share your account or the passphrase with anyone!
The resources at CSC are managed with projects.
Each project has a quota for disk space and cpu time.
Each project has a manager and members.
If you're working on the same topic then it makes sense to be in the same project.
Here's a link to the qualifications of a project manager.
Check here if you are eligible to act as a project manager.
In addition to CSC-projects there's something called a personal project.
That is a technical way to make sure
that nobody else accesses your home folder in Puhti.
You are not supposed to use the personal project for anything.
It is not meant for running batch jobs!
Please find more information on you projects in the documentation.
You can use this command to see what projects you have.
It works on the command line on Puhti and Mahti.
The project manager can invite new members to the project.
These projects are intended not to last indefinitely
and their lifetime has to be extended yearly.
If the project is no longer active the project will be closed and the data will be deleted.
There's a 90 day grace period during which you will get notified by email.
In Puhti you're not supposed to process any personal or sensitive data.
If your project needs to handle such data, please check out the documentation
on how to manage the data in the MyCSC-service.
Running jobs and virtual machines or storing files
consume something called Billing units.
These Billing units are a property of the CSC-projects.
More Billing units can be applied in MyCSC
where you can manage your CSC-projects.
Academic usage has already been paid for by the ministry of education and culture.
The free-of-charge use cases have been defined here in detail.
Remember to acknowledge CSC in your publications and
list your publications also in your Billing unit application.
You can estimate the Billing unit consumption with the Billing unit calculator.
This was the projects and accounts review.
The tutorials about accounts and projects continue from here.
They cover the basics with easy-to-follow examples.
Check out the links in the description.