This is how the course material is organised.
The material involves slides, videos, hands-on tutorials and exercises.
The material often links to the documentation at docs.csc.fi.
These tips help you to navigate within the slides and other material.
This is the general procedure of solving problems.
First try looking at the docs.
The pages are organised hierarchically.
There is also a FAQ-section that covers many topics.
You might try the search button in the docs
or googling the keywords or the error message.
If you can't find the answer then send an email to servicedesk at csc.fi.
A descriptive title helps us direct the message to the right people.
Explain what you wanted to achieve and on which computer,
what commands you gave and what error messages resulted.
There is a rather detailed help specifying how to compose a good support request.
It will help us to solve your issue faster
and you will get more quickly to do the work.
Some applications come with a tutorial.
Doing those will be the fastest way forward.
There are also instructions or documentation for installed applications.
The documentation sometimes contains application spesific batch scripts.
If they are not available you may use the general batch script template.
You can try to run the application interactively.
Do not do this in the login node but instead use for example sinteractive.
It is a one easy way to see that things are running correctly.
You can also try to run the application in a test queue.
Usually the results come quickly.
It helps you to tweak your batch script before longer runs.
It is not nice to wait in a long queue just to see that there is a typo in the script.
Always before you launch any big projects you should run a small trial
to make sure that the results are expected.
You may use the results to adjust the resource usage.
It benefits all users when the resources are used efficiently.
If your job fails you should first check for these issues.
Usually the job runs out of allocated time or memory.
If the job fails immediately there is usually a typo in the script.
The error files provide useful information on why the job failed.
Sometimes they may be difficult to interpret but sometimes there is a clear answer.
If you have difficulties to understand the error file
you may just send us the error file and we will take a look at that.
You may also look at the FAQ on common Slurm issues.
When you have solved or discovered something
we recommend that you document it for yourself
so that you can easily rediscover it later.
Here is one way to do it.
You can use cat command to save text in a file for example in your home folder.
After entering the first line you can copy paste commands or other text like a description.
Press control and C when you are finished typing.
You can use grep to look for content in that file.
Try the links in the slides, tutorials and video descriptions
to discover relevant documentation or more content.
We wish you happy learning!