Applications on the supercomputer are handled a bit
differently compared to a regular PC.
A supercomputer must fulfill the needs of different applications and
software used in different scientific purposes.
All of these software have also different dependencies and libraries they are linked to.
Some of the dependencies may also be conflicting which can create a lot of problems.
On a supercomputer you cannot load all the applications in the start-up
as a normal PC does.
Instead we separate the applications into modules.
Loading the module environment for a certain application sets up everything
that is needed for that software.
A module loads the relevant libraries,
adjust path and other environment variables needed for the software.
CSC supercomputers use Lmod framework for managing environment modules.
The application list in docs.csc.fi lists all installed  software on CSC supercomputers.
Check the documentation both when searching whether a spesific application
is installed, or how to use one.
All modules are loaded with command module load,
but what happens after that depends on the included software.
The command module spider followed by a module name
finds whether that module exists.
For example to check if program called Gromacs
for molecular dynamics simulations exists,
you can type module spider gromacs-env.
The general syntax for using modules is quite simple:
module, then the command and the module name.
Please find a list of most common commands for using modules in the documentation.
There is commands like module load, module help, module list and so on.
Whether you are running an interactive job or submitting a batch job
you always need to load the appropriate modules to use your program.
Always include the module commands in your batch script.
That way you get always the same set of modules in consecutive batch jobs.
It is a good practice to start with module purge - to have a clean slate -
and then issue the needed module loads.
The main idea in using modules is that you will not load all the modules simultaneously.
That would cancel the whole idea of avoiding conflicting dependencies
If you want to list which modules you have loaded at the moment,
you can type module list.
To check which modules are available to load right now try module avail.
It will not show modules which you can not load.
For example there might still be some missing dependencies
before you are able to load a particular module.
To search for a certain application and its versions use
module spider and the name of the application.
Also with module spider you can type the application name / the application version
to find more information on how to load a specific version of the application.
The system is designed so that it will give an error message if
you try to load a module which is not available.
Some software have a graphical user interface, for example Molden.
To use those you need a graphical session in Puhti web interface,
or some other way to access remote graphics.
Some software work in the command line interface, for example zstd.
You can start using them in the same command line after loading the module.
Some applications on the supercomputer have their own modules,
and some applications are combined in larger modules.
Then some applications can be found in multiple modules.
Some modules contain packages - for example python or R packages.
You can use them with the appropriate software after loading the module.
Avoid trial-and-errors by consulting the documentation first to find out if
the application you want to use is already included in a module.
Conda is a generally used package management tool
for distributing and installing software.
Some applications are installed and used in a Conda environment.
Unfortunately Conda has a really poor performance in Lustre parallel file system.
Therefore you should always check if the software you need
is already included in a module.
If you need to build an own Conda environment, put it in a container.
More information on installing software and containers in their own lectures.
Python-related modules have their own Docs CSC pages.
Consult those before starting because they have different instructions on usage.
Plan your workflows such that you do not need to load
multiple modules with Python packages simultaneously.
Eventually you as a supercomputer user will develop your own workflows,
such as always loading the same modules that you use in your research.
Usually in such cases people use a file called dot bashrc,
which is executed in every login.
But we do not recommend this for loading the modules automatically,
because this might cause some hard-to-find issues later on.
You should always be aware of what modules you are loading
to avoid conflicts with the dependencies.
If you already have done this and suspect some conflicts,
you can check out the csc-env command.
That allows for example resetting to the basic environment which resets the bashrc file.
However you can still use .bashrc to miminize the tedious typing.
Automatize module loading by creating an alias in the .bashrc.
Executing an alias will execute all the user-defined commands there.
You can come up with your own command like for example setmyenv,
and then define all the module loads you usually need.
Please keep in mind, that aliases might not work in a same way
in a sub shell or batch job
If you like a certain set of modules you can also save your current
module configuration and then use module restore to load your set.
You can also write your own module files and put them in your home directory.
Remember also to add the path of your modulefiles to the module search path
so that you can easily use those own modules.
To study the existing module files you use the command
module show and the module name.
That will show for example the filename of the module file which is a .lua file.
The tutorials about modules continue from here.
They cover the basic use cases with easy-to-follow examples.
Module documentation in docs.csc.fi covers also the more technical details.
The links are in the description.