On a laptop when you run something,
you double click an icon and the program starts to run.
Modern computers can run multiple tasks at the same time,
but with too many simultaneous tasks you start to run out of memory or CPU power,
which slows down the computer.
In the HPC environment really many people are using that same computer
and they all need different amounts of resources.
It is not possible to let everyone start their programs and run them in real time.
A batch job tells the batch job scheduler the resource requirements:
how much resources should be available for that particular job.
In addition to the resource request a batch job includes
some script that does the actual computing.
To ensure that there's sufficient computing power available for all users,
the batch jobs are sent to a queue.
Depending on what kind of resources you requested and on the load on the system,
the job may need to queue for some time before it starts.
On HPC systems all heavy computing needs to be done by a batch job
so that they get executed on the compute nodes.
The usage policy in docs.csc.fi says that the login nodes are
not meant for long or heavy processes.
Instead the login nodes are used for compiling, managing batch jobs,
moving data, light pre- and postprocessing.
A batch job system handles the batch jobs submitted to the supercomputer.
It keeps track on what resources exist, which requests have been made,
to which jobs allocate resources and how to run those jobs with the given resources.
The aim is to use the resources as efficiently as possible,
but also share them in a fair way.
For example when a job needs a lot of memory,
then it is allocated to a node where this memory is available.
Then if an other job does not need that much memory, it gets allocated so
that the more demanding jobs can run where they have enough resources.
The fair way of allocating resources is not the first come first served,
but instead somehow that everyone gets resources, at least at some point.
Obviously a job cannot start before the requested resources are available.
Each job has a "priority" which is used to determine the order of starting jobs.
The "fair share" configuration has the following rules of defining the priority.
When you submit a job it gets an initial priority.
This initial priority decreases if you have recently run a lot of jobs.
That makes it possible to first run some small test and get the results fast
before submitting a large set of calculations.
Once a job is in queue its priority increases over time.
At some point it will have high enough priority and it will be its turn next.
The priority depends also on which queue the job is submitted.
For example longrun has lower priority
to discourage people to run in this unless necessary.
If you do not want to queue so much for longrun resources,
then consider refining your job so that you can use the standard three day queues.
The documentation at docs.csc.fi has a guide for getting started with running jobs.
Here is an illustration on what the batch job scheduler is doing.
The batch jobs are pictured here as two dimensional rectangles.
The horisontal dimension represents the number of CPUs
and the vertical dimension represents time.
For example this tall but thin rectangle would correspond
to a fairly long job which is using just one core.
Then this short but wide rectangle would be a shorter job using many cores.
The batch job system sees these kind of job requests and
then it knows about the resources that the compute nodes have.
The aim of the batch job scheduler is to keep all the supercomputer resources
busy with computing all of the time.
That happens by allocating the jobs to the cores
in a way that there is as little gaps as possible.
It is like playing Tetris but with a variable size pieces.
But if the scheduler filled each gap with small jobs,
there would never be enough resources free for larger jobs.
The increasing job priority enables that everybody gets resources at some point.
There are more resources than just CPUs that the scheduler has to take into account.
As an example here is this small one-core job that is colored in orange.
That job requires a lot of memory and it is using all the memory that is left in this node.
That renders the node unavailable for new jobs to run because there's no memory left.
It means that these other cores in that node will be idle.
And if this job really needs and uses this memory, this is totally fine.
That is what memory is for, and one will run out before the other - memory, or cores.
But, if the job does not need that much memory,
then these cores will be unavailable for everyone for no reason.
Therefore everyone will be queuing more.
The lecture 6 will cover how to use the resources  effectively and
I hope this example shows you the importance of that topic.
The batch job system used at CSC is called Slurm.
If you ever again wonder why you must use this Slurm,
you remember that it is for sharing the awesome supercomputer resources
in a fair and efficient way.
Some resources that you can ask from Slurm are listed here.
Computing time means how long should the resources be allocated to you.
Number of cores and the amount of memory are the basic resources needed.
Then there are a bit more special resources like GPUs
or the NVMe disks for fast file input and output.
There is this example script in the slides that you as a starting point
when creating your first batch job.
This one uses only one core so it is a serial job.
Consider a batch job as an ordinary shell script, like what you use with bash.
Therefore it also starts with the line #!/bin/bash.
The difference to bash scripts is that the first part of the batch job contains
the resource requests flagged with #SBATCH.
Remember that hashtag is a comment symbol in bash,
so lines starting with #SBATCH do nothing as a bash script.
Instead the queuing system understands those flags there.
The first one is called jobname and in this example
we provide it with a value print-hostname.
The following flags define the requested time and the partition in which to run the job.
Together the number of tasks and the number of CPUs per task
define the number of cores needed for the job.
The last flag defines the billing project, which is very important.
If you don't specify a project that you have access to, you will get an error.
Then if you make some other mistake here,
typically the error message will give you an idea how to proceed.
If you omit any of the flags it will use some reasonable default values,
except of course with the account-flag.
Then the actual commands or computing steps come after the resource requests.
In general they are scripted as in any batch script.
Some commands or variables are spesific to CSC computing environment
and we try to provide you with best materials to get used to those.
Here this command srun tells the Slurm system to run a command.
Using srun makes the resource usage reports more accurate.
This echo-command is basic bash command and it prints out the following string.
In this example the string contains some useful environmental parameters.
To use this script you can copy-paste it into a textfile
named for example simple_serial.bash.
If you run it straight in Terminal it would be run on the login node.
Never run these in the login node!
The right way to run this kind of script is with
command sbatch and then the name of the script.
The documentation covers the definitions and options of the SBATCH-flags
Whenever you start to use a new application in CSC supercomputers
you should first consult the documentation at docs.csc.fi.
There you might also find a batch script template
that gives you a starting point with the application.
The templates have some default values for the resources
so you may try those and edit them to suit your needs.
Of course you will need to change the actual inputs and such in the computation step.
In general it is better to start with these application spesific templates
than with a generic template.
In any case, you will need to edit your batch job so that it will match your use case.
These are the most important commands for using the queueing system.
Submit the batch job with command sbatch example_job.sh.
Find all your jobs that are queuing or running with squeue -u $USER.
Pay attention to the job-ID, because that is needed for other commands such as
getting info on a job with scontrol show job and the job-ID.
If you want to cancel a submitted job you can use scancel and the job-ID.
The last command in this list is seff and the job-ID.
That can be used to monitor the resources that the job used.
The point is to check whether your resource request
actually matches what the job used.
The partitions, or job queues, have different properties that are listed in docs.csc.fi.
The purpose of having these different job queues is that the jobs can have
very different needs for example in terms of memory and computing time.
So estimate your resource request with thought,
and choose to which partition suits your job the best.
It is really bad practice just to ask so much resources that it will always be enough.
So please put some effort to study how much resources your jobs actually need.
You will also benefit there because your job is likely to start a little bit earlier
and there will be more resources for everyone using the supercomputer.
The available partitions are listed here in the docs.csc.fi.
Check the link to the instructions in the partition name.
The columns in the partition spreadsheet list for example the limits on run time,
maximum number of tasks and nodes and also the maximum memory available per job.
Please notice that there are a lot of these medium sized nodes
available in some queues.
Thus if you can specify your job such that it fits in the medium sized node,
then there are a lot of these resources available.
The jobs that require more time or more memory and therefore need to use
hugemem or longrun will probably be queuing longer.
It is perfectly fine to ask for a lot of memory.
This is why we have these big memory nodes.
But if you don't need that much, then you might want to consider asking
for resources that are faster and easier to provide.
One way to categorize jobs is if it uses one or multiple cores.
Also a job can be interactive or non-interactive.
Different types of jobs are explained in the following slides.
Serial jobs are the simplest type of jobs and thus a great starting point.
It is important to know the basics of different job types
also when using already installed software
- You need to know which resources to request when you start the job.
One-core jobs are serial, because the core has to process the tasks one after another.
Please note that you must not request more than one core for a serial job,
because the job cannot utilise those extra cores.
That can be seen in a resource scaling test:
No matter how many cores you allocate the job does not get any faster.
You could run many serial jobs in your laptop.
There are still reasons to run serial jobs in CSC supercomputers.
A serial jobs can be part of a larger user-defined workflow.
The job might produce some results that you want to analyse with a supercomputer,
or you want to share the results with your other CSC-project members.
You know already that there are many preinstalled software
available in the CSC environment.
You don't need to install the programs or they might even
have a license that we have already paid for.
Also serial jobs can have some big demands on memory or fast disk.
This is why we have Puhti huge memory nodes and the local NVMe disks.
You can combine individual serial jobs to create a workflow
that can utilise parallel resources.
Here is two documented ways of running multiple jobs at the same time.
Array jobs mean simply that you submit multiple jobs with a simple command.
Other high throughput workflow tools are documented in DocsCSC.
Of course, there are hundreds of other workflow tools that somehow
combine multiple single jobs into a bigger workflow.
If your individual job is a serial job, then you should run it in Puhti.
Some workflow tools make it possible to run multiple serial jobs also in Mahti.
In that case all the jobs combined should fill at least one Mahti node,
which means 128 cores and they should keep it busy
for the duration of the whole allocation.
This is a bit advanced way of running jobs so we recommend
to start by running serial jobs in Puhti.
A parallel job distributes the calculation over several cores.
That means it can use many cores for the same task simultaneously.
On the other hand you can also use the memory of
multiple nodes at the same time if your job requires it.
There are two major schemes for parallelising jobs: openMP and MPI.
If you run a pre-installed code then you don't need to worry about the details of these.
Jobs parallelised with openMP can run only within one node,
whereas MPI jobs can technically be spread over multiple nodes.
In certain cases, you can even combine those two.
The important thing is that the job resource request is different for openMP and MPI.
There are instructions and example batch scripts for both
Puhti and Mahti available in docs.csc.fi.
Use them if there is no software specific batch script template available.
A GPU is a graphics processing unit.
They are developed for very efficient parallel processing,
because graphics processing requires that.
Hence they can also run certain kinds of HPC jobs very efficiently,
for example machine learning jobs.
To use GPUs a code has to be rewritten,
compiled and linked to the libraries that can use GPU processors.
GPU cards are also a bit more expensive than regular CPU cards.
Therefore, one hour on GPU core spends 60 times more
billing units than on a single CPU core.
That means a full CPU node is a lot cheaper than one GPU core.
On Puhti you should reserve one to 10 CPU cores for each reserved GPU core,
because each Puhti GPU node has four GPU cards and 40 CPU cores.
This means that in practice using GPU cores requires more than
60 times the billing units than to use a CPU core.
Please keep in mind that if you allocate more than 10 CPU cores for one GPU,
the node may run out of CPUs which renders the GPUs unavailable.
As you login to a supercomputer you get the command line interface
that enables you to execute commands in the supercomputer.
Please remember that straight after login you are on a login node,
which can not be used for any computing!
So if you want to use the powerful computational resources and to interact
with your code, you can use the interactive jobs.
Those run on the interactive partition which has compute nodes.
There you can execute commands as if it was your local laptop,
albeit a more powerful one.
Once you are there you don't need to go through the queuing system.
For example a Jupyter notebook is something that you need to interact with
but you also might need some heavy computing resources.
The tutorials about batch jobs continue from here.
They cover the basic use cases with easy-to-follow examples.
Remember that the batch job documentation includes some
example batch scripts that you can start experimenting.