The take home message is that you can install software on CSC supercomputers.
There might be an application that is not already installed on Puhti or Mahti.
Or you might have implemented a program yourself,
and you want to use that in Puhti.
This lecture gives an overview of different types of software and installation methods.
Remember that you can always contact servicedesk@csc.fi for guidance.
Especially if the program you are trying to install is very complicated
or requires compiling it from a source code.
The most important thing to begin with is to read the software documentation.
How the software is installed depends a lot on
what type of code you are trying to install.
It might be just a Python package, or then it is a large parallel program.
Note that in general simple copy and paste examples from the internet
do not work in an HPC environment.
Before you invest a lot of effort and time into trying to install something,
it is a better option to check out the CSC application list.
Also remember that with command module spider you can see software available
in CSC supercomputing environment.
It may well be that there is some other program
– similar to the one you would like to use – already installed.
If your application is a single binary file you can try to run it on the CSC supercomputer.
Usually these binaries may not be suitable or efficient in HPC environments.
If they are compiled on a laptop they are optimized for a laptop
and not for a supercomputer.
Especially if your program is massively parallelized – like MPI codes which run on
multiple nodes – it must be recompiled for the best performance.
Binary file might be the only option if the source code is not available.
They might work fine if the program has been compiled on an identical HPC system,
or if it is a very simple program that runs for example
lightweight serial or threaded processes.
Different kind of programs can be categorised based on
the used programming languages.
The highest level of programming languages are the interpreted languages.
For example Python, Java, and R, are all interpreted coding languages.
The main advantage of those is that they are easy to program
and they do not need to be compiled.
If performance is an issue,
for example Python can be compiled to a faster C-code using cython.
Programming and running programs based on interpreted languages
usually require loading specific modules on the CSC supercomputers.
For example Python module enables access
to some of the most important Python libraries.
It also ensures that the software behaves the same on all the compute nodes.
If the computational problem you are dealing with is very complicated,
then interpreted languages are usually not the best option,
because they are not efficient for numerically heavy tasks.
To do heavy tasks somewhat efficiently with interpreted languages make sure you
utilize libraries to perform some of the most demanding computational tasks.
There might be high performance computing libraries,
or libraries that have been written using HPC programming languages.
These programming languages do not run as such,
but when they are compiled and run, they have great performance.
Examples of HPC languages are C, C++, and FORTRAN.
It requires some experience to write efficient codes with HPC languages.
They are not so easy to program and the syntax might not be so simple.
Most of very resource intensive scientific applications
have been programmed using HPC languages, because they are good
in heavy number crunching, linear algebra and such tasks.
If someone – a person involved with method development –
has already implemented the program,
then researchers need only to compile the code.
If you consider compiling complicated, contact servicedesk.
There are some things to keep in mind when installing
custom software on the CSC supercomputers.
It is not the same as installing something on your own computer.
For example you can not use sudo for getting root privileges.
Also you can not use package managers like apt or yum.
Then you don't have permissions to install into default locations.
Instead custom installations should go to the PROJAPPL
directory - where you have write access.
When you start to compile your application,
you should first load required compiler suites or language modules.
When you install custom software, it is not automatically added to the PATH.
That means you can't run the program from anywhere
without providing the path to the binary file.
If you install software directly to the system it is called native installation.
That would be for example the binary file that you have compiled and run.
It is a good way of installing if the program does not have many dependencies.
Applications can also be available as containers.
Containers provide a convenient way of installing software and its dependencies.
There are many containers available in public.
Please consider using containers even if other installation methods were available.
See the container lecture and the documentation for more information.
Conda is a package manager used especially for many Python packages.
It is very popular, but unfortunately it is also problematic in HPC systems.
A Conda environment contains a huge number of files
which really slows down Lustre file system.
They are also difficult to maintain because of many dependencies.
Containers are a preferred installation method,
because they package everything in a single file.
Also Conda installations can be put into a container and used in HPC environment.
Check out the batch job lecture for details on submitting batch jobs.
Test the software with short batch jobs.
It you submit a long and heavy job with no knowledge of how it works,
you are wasting time and resources
– not only yours but other users and admins as well.
Try to reproduce some results that you know beforehand.
That way you can deduce if the program works as intended.
Some software might have a tutorial that you can run.
Run your tests e.g. in the test queue or in an interactive session.
Check also the efficiency of the code by comparing it to your previous compilations.
In other words, be sure to benchmark your new software.
The tutorials about installing software have some easy-to-follow examples.
Be sure to check out the documentation in DocsCSC pages.
There is information on how to compile applications in Puhti or Mahti,
and how to use different HPC libraries.
There is also guidelines for loading different compilers.
For example whether to compile using an Intel or GNU compiler, what kind of
optimization flags you can use, or how to link different HPC libraries to your codes.
There is of course a lot of information available online.
If you get some errors or problems in the compilation,
copy paste the error messages and Google for some tips.
Also be sure to contact the servicedesk in case of any issues.